Come on. I'm so cold.
あー…ったく冷えやがるな
Ragnarok
How long do we have to wait here?
いつまでここでにらめっこしてんだぁ？
We're not earning anything.
稼ぎになんねぇぞ
The prince got scared.
王子が怖気づいてんだろ
So we were right about Wessex.
こりゃあウェセックスがあたりだったなぁ
I'm sure about it.
違えねぇ
We got the short end of the stick--
まったく、貧乏くじ引いち…
Take that!
りゃああああっ！
-There's another one!
-Get away! Get away!
またくるぞ！
さがれ！さがれ！
Hey!
オラーッ！
Hurry up and attack!
とっととかかってこい！！
You'll never go to Valhalla at this rate!
そんなんじゃヴァルハラに行けねぇぞ！
Are you just going to stand there?
そこで突っ立ってるだけか！
You're just a bunch of scarecrows!
てめぇらカカシかよ！
-Damn that bastard!
-He's so full of himself!
くそ！あの野郎！
もう我慢ならねぇ！
None of you has any balls!
てめぇら！そろいもそろって！タマなしかぁ～～っ！
Ragnar!
ラグナル殿！
Letting him insult us like this
このまま侮辱を見過ごせば
is a disgrace to us warriors! Let's attack!
兵士としての名折れ！突撃しましょう！
We're ready to fight!
皆、士気は充分です！
We have 4000 men. I'm sure we can beat Thorkell!
我ら4千、必ずやトルケルを討ち取ります！
Not yet. We're talking about Thorkell.
まだだ…相手はあのトルケル。
We can't make a careless move.
うかつに手は出せん
His Highness put us in charge of the siege.
陛下じきじきに包囲軍を任されたのです。
This is our chance to distinguish ourselves
as warriors!
今こそ武勲をあげる機会では…！
No.
ならん！
When the time comes,
His Highness shall give the order.
時が来れば殿下が命を下す。
Now is the time to wait.
今は耐えるのだ…！
Ragnar!
ラグナル殿…！
And then the Lord was told,
そこで主は彼に言われたのです。
"Put your sword back into its place,
あなたの剣をおさめなさい
for all those who take up the sword
shall perish by the sword."
剣をとる者は皆、剣で滅びるのです
Father. Excuse me. Can you leave us alone
for a moment?
神父。すまんが少し外してくれるか
-Orders? Who cares!
-The prince is a coward!
命令が何だってんだ！
腰ヌケ王子が！
I'm not going to sit here silent!
いつまでも黙ってられるか！
Yeah! Let's do it!
おお！やろう！
Yeah! That's right!
Don't worry.
ご心配いりませぬ。
When winter comes,
we will receive the order to withdraw.
冬になれば撤退命令がなされるはず。
We'll just have to endure until then.
それまでのご辛抱です…
Come on! You're kidding me!
God, please protect His Highness.
神よ…どうか殿下をお守り下さい…
Damn! What's wrong with you? You guys are no fun!
くそっ！なんだよっつまんねー奴らだな！
You're hard at work too.
大将も精が出るなあ
Are they being mean again?
まーた嫌がらせか？
Shut up, Asgeir.
うっせ！アスゲート！
We can't have a battle if they don't attack!
あっちが攻めてこねぇと戦になんねぇだろうが！
Don't be so loud. I bet they're just being more careful.
でけぇよ声が。まあ慎重になってんだろ。
They're under the command of the Prince of Denmark.
なんせあっちの大将はデンマークの王子様だしな
What?
え…？
What? Is the Prince here?
なに？王子来てんの？
Huh? I thought I already told you.
あれ？言ってなかったか？
The second prince, His Highness Canute.
確か第2王子のクヌート殿下…
Mother's here.
母上がいる
And my sister too.
姉上も
Ari is slacking off again watching the sheep.
またアーレたちが羊の番をサボっている。
Just the other day, they were saying that
one went missing.
この間も1頭いなくなったって大騒ぎしてたくせに
That's right! It's time for dinner!
I have to go tell Father!
あ、そーだ晩ゴハンだ。父上を呼びにいかなくっちゃ！
Father!
父上ー！
父上ーっ！
We're having meat tonight.
We're celebrating Yule.
今晩はお肉だよ！ユルのお祝いだからね
Oh, really? It's already the winter solstice?
あーそうか。もう冬至かぁ。
It's pretty warm, so I had forgotten about it.
ずいぶん暖かいから忘れてたよ
This is a nice place.
ここはいい所だ。
There's enough grass for the animals.
I'm glad we moved here.
牧草にも不自由しない。移り住んで正解だったな
My sister says it's inconvenient living here
because we can't get any slaves.
姉上は“ここじゃ奴隷が手に入らないから不便だ”
って言ってるよ。
We've never even had a slave, though.
奴隷買ったことないのにねウチ
She would say that.
あいつらしいな
I like it here.
ボクはここ好き。
Mother seems to be feeling better after we moved here.
ここに来てから母上も調子いいみたいだし
Thorfinn.
トルフィン
What?
何？
You're my oldest son.
お前は長男だ。
You have to protect your mother and your sister.
You understand, right?
母上や姉上を守ってやらなきゃだめだぞ。わかるな？
Yeah.
うん！
They're both waiting for you to come home.
2人ともお前の帰りを待ちわびている。
Having people like that
そんな人がいてくれるのは
is a happy thing.
とても幸せなことなんだ
Do you understand?
わかるか？
So stop thinking about revenge.
だからな。もう復讐なんてやめろ。
Do you think that would make me happy?
そんなことオレが喜ぶと思うのか？
The village!
村が！
Father! What are we going to do? We're under attack!
父上どうしよう！襲われてる！
Mother! Sister!
母上！姉上！
Father!
父上ーッ！！
Where was that?
オレの国じゃ…なかったな…
Somewhere warm...
暖かくて…
with rolling plains of grass...
草原が波打って…
as far as the eye can see...
どこまでも…
NOVEMBER, 1013
OUTSKIRTS OF BATH
What in the world is our leader thinking?
しっかし、なに考えてんだろうな。
ウチの親分は
It's almost winter.
もう冬になるぜ？
The main army withdrew to the north
a long time ago.
本隊はとっくに北に引きあげちまった。
But we're still here picking off
gloomy villages like this.
だのにオレらだけ居残ってこんなシケた村つまんでる
Well, we have to earn what we can
before going back.
ま、少しでもこづかい稼いで帰ろうってことなんだろ
Then we should attack a bigger city!
だったらもっとデカい町襲おうぜ。
Bristol is near here, right?
近くにブリストルとかあんだろ？
Are you stupid?
バカか。
What can we do with only 100 men?
100人ばかしで何ができるってんだよ
What? Stupid?
あ？バカ？
Did you just call me stupid?
今バカっつったかオイ？
Huh, you heard me?
お？聞こえたか？
I guess your ears aren't stupid.
耳だけはバカじゃねーみてーだな
What did you say?
なんだとテメェ！
What's wrong with you?
んだコラァ！
What? I'm going to kill you!
Well, all that's left for this year
is to plunder two or three more villages.
まぁ今年はあと2、3コ村を食って終わりだな。
I hope next year's going to be better.
また来年に期待しようや
Do you think we'll still have a chance
next year?
あるかね？来年が
What?
あ？
We've been plundering England
for ten years already.
オレたちゃもう10年もイングランドを荒らし回ってんだぜ？
This year was especially horrible.
特に今年はすさまじかった。
I heard that the King of England
escaped overseas.
イングランド王も国外に逃げたっていうじゃねえか
That means
that the King of Denmark has won.
もうこりゃデンマーク王の勝ちだよ。
The war is coming to an end.
戦は終わりだ
Really? I think it's still too early.
そうかァ？まだ早いんじゃねーの？
Thorkell's in London.
ロンドンにゃあのトルケルがいるぜ？
You saw how strong he is, right?
野郎のウソくせぇ強さは見ただろうが
Thorkell, huh? He is strong.
トルケルねぇ…確かに強ェけど。
But he's Norse, just like us.
そもそもありゃオレらと同じノルド人だぜ？
Once the English are about to die,
he'd ditch them in a heartbeat.
死に体のイングランドをいつ見限ってもおかしくねェ…
Kill him.
あーあー
Again?
またか
Kill him, Tore!
Take that!
オラァーッ！
Hey, guys! Why are they fighting?
コラコラコラ。理由はなんだ理由は
Ake called Tore stupid.
アークがトーレに“バカ”って言った。
Tore got mad.
トーレが怒ったけど
But Ake wouldn't apologize
and insulted him even more.
アークは謝罪しねェで逆に侮辱した
What'd he say?
なんて？
Cattle thief.
牛泥棒
I see.
あーあ。
So that's what he said.
それ言っちゃったかー
Then it can't be helped.
んじゃ仕方ねェ。
Just make sure you tell Askeladd afterwards,
no matter who dies.
どっちが死んでもあとでちゃんとアシェラッドに報告しとけよ。
What a pain.
めんどくせぇ…
A fertile land.
豊かな土地だ。
It's like the land I saw in my dream.
夢に出てきた土地に似てる…
It's really different from Iceland.
アイスランドとはえらい違いだ。
I bet the snow is beginning
to pile up around now.
きっと今頃は雪が積もり始めているだろうな…
You're up early, Thorfinn.
早起きだな。トルフィン
The sun hasn't even come up yet.
まだ陽も上ってねェぜ
So you couldn't sleep
because they're too loud?
あいつらが騒がしくて眠れないか。
Well, go easy on them.
ま、カンベンしてやれや
They were frustrated since we've been
marching a lot these days.
ここんとこ行軍ばかりであいつらもイラついてたからなァ。
You got to relax sometimes.
たまにゃああして気晴らしせんと
Don't talk to me like we're close!
気やすく話しかけんな。
I think you've got the wrong idea.
テメェら最近勘違いしてんじゃねぇのか？
I'm not your friend.
オレァテメェらの仲間じゃねぇ
I bet you think you have me
under your control.
テメェはオレをうまいこと操ってるつもりだろ？
You're full of yourself now.
今はそうやってうぬぼれてろ。
But it'll stop when I slit
your throat someday,
オレにノドを裂かれて
and you fall over and die.
くたばるその日までな
I'm so scared.
怖いね。
I never imagined that little kid would glare
at me someday. You've grown a lot.
あのチビガキがオレにガンとばすとは成長したもんだ
Well, time is on your side.
ま、時間は若いお前の味方だ。
You're going to grow,
and I'm going to get old.
お前は成長しオレは老いる。
Someday, I'm going to lose to you.
いつかお前に負ける日も来るだろう
It's only natural.
当然のことだ。
Even the strongest dies someday.
どんな強者もいずれは死ぬ
Look around you, Thorfinn.
周りを見てみろトルフィン。
These stones weren't made by the people
この石くれは今のイングランドの住人、
who live in England now, the Saxons.
サクソン人が造ったものじゃない。
They were made by the people who lived here
before the Saxons.
サクソンよりも前の住人のものだ
I heard they were a strong people.
強い民族だったそうだ。
But they were destroyed
by the Saxons 500 years ago.
だが500年前サクソンに滅ぼされた。
They were the Romans.
ローマ人だ。
The name of their country was Britannia.
国の名は“ブリタニア”
They had an advanced civilization.
高度な文明だった。
More advanced than what we have now.
今よりもずっとな
Stop beating around the bush.
回りくどいんだよ。
What are you trying to say?
何が言いてぇ
You're so impatient.
せっかちだねぇ。
You should listen to what your elders say.
年寄りの話は聞くもんだぜ
Well, in other words,
まあつまりだな…
the world of man
人間の世界はゆるやかに、
is getting older gradually, but surely.
だが確実に老いてきてるってことさ
The Saxons destroyed the Romans,
ローマ人をサクソンが滅ぼし、
and we're going to destroy the Saxons next.
そのサクソンを今度はオレたちが滅ぼす。
The glory of the Roman Empire
is a thing of the distant past.
遠い過去になる
Anyways, according to what
the Christians are saying,
なんでもキリスト教徒どもの言うことにゃ…
the Last Judgment is coming
in only 20 years.
あと20年もしたら“最後の審判”
とやらが下るそうじゃねェか
On that day, God will kill everyone,
その日、人間はすべて神に殺され
and our world will be completely destroyed.
今の世は完全に滅ぶんだそうだ
Ragnarok.
ラグナロク…
Look, Thorfinn.
見ろトルフィン。
It's ironic, right?
こっけいじゃねェか
Dawn in the age of twilight.
たそがれの時代の夜明けだ
It's a horse.
馬だ。1騎
Is it an English soldier?
イングランドの兵か？
No. He's an ally.
いや。ありゃあ友軍だ
That's weird.
I thought we were the only ones in this area.
妙だな。ここらにゃオレらしかいないはずだが
Hey! Wait!
おォい！待たれよ貴公！
We're Askeladd's unit, under King Sweyn!
我らはスヴェン王配下アシェラッド隊！
Where did you come from?
貴公はいずれより参られたか！
Oh, are you from the main army?
おお！貴公は本隊所属か！
I'm from Ragnar's unit
under His Highness Prince Canute!
我はクヌート王子殿下のラグナル隊！
-I've got a message for the main force!
-Prince Canute?
本隊へ伝令に行く途次だ！
クヌート王子…
Are they close by?
この近くなのか！？
Unfortunately, the main army is far north.
あいにくだが本隊はずっと北だ。
They're on their way home.
もう本拠地へ帰りつつある
Then what are you doing here?
なら貴公はこんな所で何を？
We're just trying to earn some pocket money
in that village over there.
なにちょいと、そこの村で小銭稼ぎをね
You separated from the army on your own?
勝手に部隊から離れたのか！？
Well, don't be so stiff.
まあまあカタいこと言うなよ。
Your horse looks tired.
馬も疲れてるようだぜ？
Do you want to trade it for a new one?
なんなら新しいのと取り替えてやろうか？
Thorkell?
な！トルケルが！？
Yes. He's almost there.
ああ。もうそこまで来てる。
There's 500 men. He took along only
his immediate followers.
数は500ほど。奴の直参だけ連れてきたようだ
They're following the main army.
本隊の足跡をたどってきてる。
They're going to reach Marlborough soon.
もうじきマールバラに至るだろう
Seriously?
おいマジかよ
-They're so close!
-Attacking the main army with only 500?
500で本隊とやり合う気か？
バカなのか？トルケルって
What about the unit laying siege to London?
ロンドンの包囲軍は？
I thought Prince Canute had 4000 men.
クヌート王子の4千がいたはずだが
They were defeated a long time ago.
そんなものとっくに撃破されたよ。
I'm one of the survivors.
オレがその生き残りだ…
What?
なんだ…？
With Thorkell leading them,
奴らトルケルを先頭に
they came out of the fortress.
砦から打って出てきたんだ
Take that!
うおらああぁぁっ！
They were all as strong as bears.
どいつもこいつも熊みてぇに強かった
We couldn't do anything.
誰もなすすべなかった…
They're making a beeline for the main army.
本隊まで一直線だ
Your Highness! Your Highness!
殿下…殿下…！
Lord, may they rest in peace.
主よ。彼らに安らかな眠りを。
-I pray that their souls may be saved--
-Your Highness!
その魂が…
殿下！殿下！
Thorkell is close!
We must leave at once!
トルケルめがそこまで！すぐにここを！
I found you, Prince!
王子様みーっけ
So, what happened to His Highness Canute?
それで？クヌート殿下はどうなった？
They captured him.
奴らのとりこだ。
He's with Thorkell's army.
トルケル軍と共にいらっしゃる
The remaining soldiers are trying to regroup
to go get His Highness back.
殿下を奪還すべく残存兵力が再結集を試みているが…
But we have less than 400 men.
集まった兵は400に満たない…
And their morale is low.
士気も高いとは言えん
I'm on my way to ask the main army for help.
これから本隊へ応援を頼みに行くところだ。
Join us. We'd be grateful to have
even 100 extra men.
。貴公らも加わってくれ。今は100人でもありがたい
What do you want to do? It's your decision.
どうする？決めるのはあんただ。
Askeladd.
アシェラッド
Come on. This isn't the time for us
to just fade into the twilight.
まったく…おちおちたそがれてもいられねェな…
What?
あん？
Can't you hear it, Bjorn?
聞こえねェかビョルン？
The sound of the footsteps
ラグナロクの
of Ragnarok.
足音がよ…
Bury him. And the horse he was riding.
埋めとけ。こいつの乗ってきた馬もだ
What? Okay.
こっ…あーあ…
Listen up, guys!
いいかァ野郎ども！よく聞け！
We're going to go save
His Highness Prince Canute!
我々は今からクヌート王子殿下の救出に向かう！
We're up against 500 of Thorkell's men!
But we're not going to ask for help!
相手はトルケル以下500！だが他の部隊の手は借りん！
It's time to place our bets!
ここがバクチの打ちどころだ！
His Highness Canute is second in line
クヌート殿下はデンマーク王位継承権
for the throne of Denmark.
第2位のお方！
We're going to get a lot of money no matter
which side we hand him over to.
どちらの軍に渡しても報酬はたんまりだ！
Can you imagine...
お前ら想像できるか？
the rewards we'd be granted
デンマークとイングランド、
by the rulers of Denmark and England?
2大国の覇者が賜るごほうびを。
We can't let someone else take it away from
right under our noses!
みすみす他の奴らに譲る手はねェぜ
Yeah!
おお…おお…！
Let's do it! This is going to be ours!
よぉしやろう！オレたちの手柄だ！
We'll do it!
やってやろうぜ！
What are you going to do
now that you've stirred them up?
どーすんだよ。たきつけちまって…
We're up against Thorkell.
Do you have a plan for winning?
相手はトルケルだぞ？勝算あんのか？
Who knows.
さぁな
"Who knows"? Are you--
さぁなって。お前…
This is the age of twilight, Bjorn.
たそがれの時代だぜビョルン
Let's go out with a bang.
どうせならブァーッと暴れてみようじゃねェか